Inventory of the Theodore Fred Abel papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Theodore Fred Abel papers
1930-1988
50000
Hoover Institution Archives
30 manuscript boxes (12.5 linear feet)
Diaries, other writings, and printed matter related to sociological theory and world politics. Also includes autobiographical sketches (biograms) by members of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei relating to their reasons for becoming national socialists, collected by Theodore Abel as research material for his book Why Hitler Came into Power (1938). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Abel, Theodore, 1896-1988.
Access
Microfilm use only. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1950, with increments in March 1986 and most likely 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1896 Born, Lodz, Poland
1918-1920 Served in the Polish Army
1920 Liaison officer, American Young Men's Christian Association
1920-1923 Studied at University of Warsaw and University of Poznan
1923 Immigrated to United States
1925-1929 Taught at the University of Illinois
1929 Ph.D., Columbia University
1929-1951 Sociology professor, Columbia University
1933 Author, Protestant Home Missions to Catholic Immigrants
1934 Collected autobiographies of followers of Adolf Hitler
1938 Author, Why Hitler Came to Power
circa 1939-1941 Served on Herbert Hoover's Commission for Polish Relief
1951-1967 Professor and chairman, Department of Sociology at Hunter College, City University of New York
1957-1958 President, Eastern Sociological Society
1967- Taught at University of Notre Dame, University of Waterloo (Canada), and University of New Mexico
1969 Received merit award from the Eastern Sociological Society
1970 Author, The Foundation of Sociological Theory
1988 Died
Source: "Abel, Theodore." Robert Bierstedt. International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. Volume 18. Edited by David L. Sills.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Theodore Abel papers contain diaries, other writings, and printed matter related to sociological theory and world politics. The collection also includes autobiographical sketches (biograms) by members of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei, relating to their reasons for becoming national socialists, collected by Abel as research material for his book Why Hitler Came into Power: An Answer Based on the Original Life Stories of Six Hundred of His Followers (1938).
Abel collected the autobiographies of hundreds of followers of Adolf Hitler in 1934 as source material to improve upon the understanding of the Hitler movement. While visiting Germany in the summer of 1933, Abel was struck by the willingness of many Germans to discuss their political experiences. To follow up on this, in June 1934 he announced a prize contest designed to induce Hitler's followers to submit their life stories. He posted this announcement at all local headquarters of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei and in the party press:
For the Best Personal Life History of an Adherent of the Hitler Movement
Any person, regardless of sex or age, who was a member of the National Socialist party before January 1, 1933, or who was in sympathy with the movement, may participate in this contest.
Contestants are to give accurate and detailed descriptions of their personal lives, particularly after the World War. Special attention should be given to accounts of family life, education, economic conditions, membership in associations, participation in the Hitler movement, and important experiences, thoughts, and feelings about events and ideas of the post-war period.
The prizes will be awarded to authors who have submitted the most detailed and trustworthy accounts. Style, spelling, or dramatic story value will not be considered. Completeness and frankness are the sole criteria, so that even the simplest and most undramatic story will receive full consideration.
The prizes will be awarded as follows:
First prize...... 125 marks
Second prize.... 50 marks
Third prize...... 25 marks
Five prizes..... 20 marks each
Ten prizes...... 10 marks each
The prize money is deposited in the German Bank. The contest is organized under the tutelage of the sociology department of Columbia University, whose members will be the final judges. The purpose of the contest is the collection of material on the history of National Socialism, so that the American public may be informed about it on the basis of factual, personal documents.
Abel received 683 manuscripts, the content of which he felt justified the project and the personal expense of paying for the prizes. Of these 683 manuscripts, 48 were written by women and were not considered by Abel for the study published as Why Hitler Came into Power (he planned a separate article about the women's histories). Also excluded from study for the book were a score of biographies of one or two pages that contained very little information.
The autobiographies, called biograms in this finding aid, contain data on age, occupation, socioeconomic class, education, employment, membership in various associations, place of residence, marital status, military service in World War I, participation in military activities after World War I, first contacts with the National Socialist movement, the main reason for joining the movement, expressions of anti-Semitism, etc. Abel's assessment of the reliability and objectivity of the biograms is included in the introduction to his book, which is also the source of this scope and content note.
The incremental materials consist of diaries, speeches and writings, course materials, and printed matter. Two of Abel's later diaries can be found in this file, as well as diary transcriptions. The file includes Abel's speeches and writings on sociology, including writings on Verstehen and various book reviews. The course materials include extensive handwritten notes by Abel on topics such as Max Weber and social theory.
Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; National socialism.; Sociology.; World politics--20th century.; Germany--Politics and government.
- Nazi Biograms
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiographical sketches collected by Theodore Abel in 1934 from people who self-identified as members of the Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei before January 1, 1933, or who were in sympathy with the movement. Typically, each autobiography contains information on the writer's occupation, socioeconomic class, education, employment, membership in various associations, place of residence, marital status, military service in World War I, participation in military activities after World War I, first contacts with the National Socialist movement, the main reason for joining the movement, expressions of anti-Semitism, etc.
  Abel used these autobiographies to write a book, Why Hitler Came into Power: An Answer Based on the Original Life Stories of Six Hundred of His Followers (1938).
  For the names of respondents, see List of Individuals (men and women) and List of Women.
  - Originals
    - #1-60 (Reel 1)
      Box 1
    - #61-136 (#89 missing) (Reels 1A-2)
      Box 2
    - #137-198 (#160 missing) (Reels 2-3)
      Box 3
    - #199-263 (#204 missing) (Reels 3-4)
      Box 4
    - #264-357 (#326, 336-339 missing) (Reels 4-5)
      Box 5
    - #358-465 (#368 missing) (Reels 5-6)
      Box 6
    - #466-569 (#480 missing) (Reel 6)
      Box 7
    - #570-593 (#580 missing) (Reel 7)
      Box 8
  - Photocopies
    This is an incomplete set of copies, estimated to include about 90 percent of the originals in boxes 1-8
    - #1-172 (Reel 7)
      Box 9
    - #173-302
      Box 10
    - #303-465
      Box 11
    - #466-593
      Box 12
- List of Individuals
  For microfilm reel numbers, see Nazi Biograms series. For a list of just women respondents, see List of Women.
  - #1: Hermann Führbach, birthdate: 1907, number of pages: 3 (typed) (Reading room workstation)
  - #2: Fritz Schroner, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1919, number of pages: 2
  - #3: Wilhelm Schmitz, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 4
  - #4: Heinrich Dörnhaus, birthdate: 1910, Nazi party number: 237971, number of pages: 3
  - #5: Heinrich Wilmskötter, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 5
  - #6: Hermann Kleinfeld, birthdate: 1896, World War I service: from 1915, number of pages: 6
  - #7: Fritz Hafkesbrink, birthdate: after 1910, number of pages: 5
  - #8: Hugo Doll, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: yes, number of pages: 4
  - #9: Carl Koch, birthdate: 1877, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 3
  - #10: Gustav Kohlenberg, birthdate: 1907, number of pages: 8
  - #11: Ernst Seyffardt, birthdate: 1888, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: i495873, number of pages: 3
  - #12: Kurt Löcher, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: since 1915, number of pages: 4
  - #13: F. Lüttgens, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 15
  - #14: Karl Fischer, birthdate: 1890, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 5
  - #15: Wilhelm Wittfeld, birthdate: 1901, Nazi party number: 47879, number of pages: 6
  - #16: O. Wolf, birthdate: 1889, World War I service: 1914-1916, number of pages: 5
  - #17: Karl Fliethmann, birthdate: 1891, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 8
  - #18: Gottfried Raunis, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 4
  - #19: Wilhelm Naatz, birthdate: 1904, number of pages: 3
  - #20: Wilhelm Grotstollen, birthdate: 1905, Nazi party number: 34537, number of pages: 3
  - #21: Emil Jung, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 4
  - #22: Fritz Schulte, birthdate: 1900, number of pages: 11
  - #23: Werner Kocks, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 3
  - #24: A. Schralin ?, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 14
  - #25: Friedrich W. Braune, birthdate: 1871, World War I service: 1915-1918, number of pages: 12
  - #26: August Ude, birthdate: 1886, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 213020, number of pages: 2
  - #27: Franz Happe, birthdate: 1873, World War I service: 1915-1918, number of pages: 7
  - #28: Georg Lossau, birthdate: 1885, World War I service: 1914-1917, number of pages: 48
  - #29: Ernst Ahlbom, birthdate: 1906, number of pages: 7
  - #30: Maria Bauer, birthdate: 1860, number of pages: 5
  - #31: Rudolf Kahn, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: from 1915, number of pages: 15
  - #32: Stummeyer, birthdate: 1894, World War I service: 1914-1918, Nazi party number: 106903, number of pages: 7
  - #33: Arno Belger, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 9
  - #34: Fr. W. Dietrich, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 153627, number of pages: 6
  - #35: Hermann Reinhardt, birthdate: circa 1896, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 6
  - #36: Hertha von Reuss, birthdate: unknown, number of pages: 3
  - #37: Friedrich Jöms, birthdate: 1884, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 2
  - #38: Karl Schade, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 2
  - #39: Heinrich Becker, birthdate: 1891, World War I service: 1914-1917, number of pages: 5
  - #40: Paul Grosche, birthdate: before 1900, World War I service: 1916-1918, Nazi party number: 19947, number of pages: 3
  - #41: Marlene Heder, birthdate: 1914, number of pages: 8
  - #42: Heinz Hassmann, birthdate: 1907, number of pages: 13
  - #43: Hugo Seiler, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 6
  - #44: Hilde Boehm-Stoltz, birthdate: unknown, Nazi party number: 429341, number of pages: 5
  - #45: Fritz Linde, birthdate: before 1900, World War I service: yes, when unknown, Nazi party number: 385890, number of pages: 4
  - #46: Grete Kirchner, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 3
  - #47: Kurt Winkler, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 3
  - #48: Kuhnekerth, birthdate: 1901, number of pages: 5
  - #49: G. Meyer, birthdate: 1872, World War I service: 1915-1918, number of pages: 2
  - #50: Heinrich Potz, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: 1914-1919, number of pages: 6
  - #51: Karl Puff, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 5
  - #52: Hans Haas, birthdate: 1899, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 9
  - #53: Johann Pitz, birthdate: 1903, number of pages: 3
  - #54: Fritz Glasmacher, birthdate: 1901, number of pages: 8
  - #55: Gottfried Klinger, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 4
  - #56: Friedrich Achterberg, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: n.kv. [nicht kriegsverwendungsfähig, not fit to serve in war], number of pages: 5
  - #57: Otto Elbing, birthdate: 1895, World War I service: from 1915, number of pages: 10
  - #58: Schruff, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: from 1916, number of pages: 2
  - #59: Ewald Kersten, birthdate: 1904, number of pages: 4
  - #60: Hubert Schummel, birthdate: 1896, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 5692, number of pages: 27
  - #61: Walter Hochhaus, birthdate: 1911, number of pages: 5
  - #62: Ewald Banteleit, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 10
  - #63: August Marleiter, birthdate: before 1890, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 6
  - #64: unknown, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 1
  - #65: Winfried Harhausen, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 11
  - #66: Purper, birthdate: 1905, number of pages: 6
  - #67: Werner Petersohn, birthdate: 1903, number of pages: 3
  - #68: Rudolf Strahle, birthdate: 1894, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 3
  - #69: Wilhelm Haselhofer, birthdate: 1906, number of pages: 4
  - #70: Gustav Skrieme, birthdate: 1886, number of pages: 3
  - #71: unknown, birthdate: 1901, number of pages: 3
  - #72: Heinz Fuhrmann, birthdate: 1909, Nazi party number: 98838, number of pages: 5
  - #73: Ernst Woldt, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 4
  - #74: Willy Fischer, birthdate: 1902, Nazi party number: 13544, number of pages: 3
  - #75: Willy Köhler, birthdate: 1884, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 4
  - #76: Sens, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: from 1916, number of pages: 2
  - #77: Adolf Trappe, birthdate: 1895, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 2
  - #78: Walter Naumann, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: 1918, Nazi party number: 204225, number of pages: 5
  - #79: Karl Brandt, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: 1918, number of pages: 4
  - #80: Hans Thaysen, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: 1918, Frkp., number of pages: 5
  - #81: Walter Werthschitzky, birthdate: 1903, number of pages: 7
  - #82: Gottlieb Bartling, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 3
  - #83: Martin Fritzsche, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: 1918, number of pages: 7
  - #84: Werner Hansel, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 5
  - #85: Emil Hanf, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 4
  - #86: Johannes Müller, birthdate: 1912, number of pages: 3
  - #87: Wilhelm Julius, birthdate: 1871, number of pages: 3
  - #88: Georg Zeidier, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 5
  - #89: missing
  - #90: Graf Peter von Dyck, birthdate: 1892, World War I service: 1914-1917, number of pages: 6
  - #91: Heinrich Reichwald, birthdate: 1903, Nazi party number: 482466, number of pages: 2
  - #92: Alfons Haberland, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 2
  - #93: Johann F. Fiedler, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 2
  - #94: Friedrich Schulze, birthdate: 1886, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 2
  - #95: Hermann Axmann, birthdate: 1880, World War I service: 1914-1917, Nazi party number: 162849, number of pages: 4
  - #96: Hans Plath, birthdate: 1911, Nazi party number: 151910, number of pages: 7
  - #97: Günther Eggebrecht, birthdate: 1904, number of pages: 7
  - #98: Wilhelm Jöckel, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 3
  - #99: Hans Muller, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 2
  - #100: Johann Leuer, birthdate: 1870, number of pages: 2
  - #100A: Agnes Mosler-Sturm, birthdate: unknown, number of pages: 5 (first page missing)
  - #101: Paul Kitzing, birthdate: 1902, Nazi party number: 29386, number of pages: 7
  - #102L Heinrich Dinse, birthdate: 1876, World War I service: 1915-1917, number of pages: 3
  - #103: Max Reimann, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: 1918, number of pages: 3
  - #104: Paul Fritze, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: from 1917, Nazi party number: 180757, number of pages: 1
  - #105: Friedrich Hagen, birthdate: before 1900, World War I service: yes, when unknown, number of pages: 7
  - #106: Paul Michligk, birthdate: 1899, number of pages: 27
  - #107: Lissy Schneider, birthdate: 1916, number of pages: 5 (not typed)
  - #108: Fritz Herzog, birthdate: 1903, number of pages: 4
  - #109: Wilhelm Hastin, birthdate: 1883, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 618994, number of pages: 7
  - #110: Gustav Heinsch, birthdate: 1890, World War I service: 1914-1918, Nazi party number: 430139, number of pages: 30 (typed)
  - #111: Heinrich Kiefer, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: from 1916, number of pages: 10 (not typed)
  - #112: Otto Seifert, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 2
  - #113: Werner Leunertz, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 8
  - #114: Johann Stuppi, birthdate: before 1890, World War I service: from 1916, Nazi party number: 249556, number of pages: 14
  - #115: Ludwig Rehbock, birthdate: circa 1880, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 4
  - #116: Frau M. Meinecke, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 9
  - #117: Waldemar Groetschel, birthdate: 1887, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 3
  - #118: Hermann Hanisch, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 11
  - #119: Gustav Zimmermann, birthdate: 1872, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 2
  - #120: Otto G., birthdate: 1900, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 639694, number of pages: 6
  - #121: Hermann Sprung, birthdate: 1888, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 2
  - #122: Friedrich Malakam, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 156561, number of pages: 3
  - #123: Valentin von Berg, birthdate: 1899, Nazi party number: 29775, number of pages: 24
  - #124: Wilhelm Fiege, birthdate: 1899, World War I service: from 1917, Nazi party number: 187783, number of pages: 3
  - #125: Herrmann, birthdate: 1894, World War I service: 1914-1918, Nazi party number: 22808, number of pages: 3
  - #126: Hans Jäger, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 3
  - #127: Emil Krug, birthdate: 1905, number of pages: 3
  - #128: Karl Liebelenz, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 2
  - #129: Heinrich Wenzel, birthdate: 1907, number of pages: 6
  - #130: Margarete Beckel, birthdate: 1879, number of pages: 4
  - #131: Kurt Reith, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: from 1915, number of pages: 3
  - #132: Waldemar v. Schoeler, birthdate: 1868, World War I service: 1914-1916, Nazi party number: 177038, number of pages: 8 (typed)
  - #133: Heinrich Leithl, birthdate: 1900, number of pages: 19 (not typed)
  - #134: Gustav Mielenz, birthdate: 1890, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 15
  - #135: Fidor Pilz, birthdate: 1896, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 5
  - #136: Franz Brehmer, birthdate: 1914, number of pages: 2
  - #137: Roggmann, birthdate: after 1900, Nazi party number: 30843, number of pages: 8
  - #138: Konrad Höfling, birthdate: 1882, World War I service: 1915-1918, number of pages: 4
  - #139: Helmuth von Goldbeck, birthdate: 1893, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 7
  - #140: Theodor Jeck, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 4
  - #141: Gertrud von Bardeleben, birthdate: 1876, number of pages: 4
  - #142: August Villwak, birthdate: 1906, number of pages: 11
  - #143: Kurt Eckert, birthdate: 1899, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 3
  - #144: Arnold Schier, birthdate: 1903, number of pages: 8
  - #145: Ruth Gratwohl, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 6
  - #146: Josef Schlenner, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 5
  - #147: Jakob Haeser, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 4
  - #148: Johann Kreuzholz, birthdate: 1900, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 3
  - #149: Wilfried Müller, birthdate: 1911, number of pages: 4
  - #150: Wilhelm Schulz, birthdate: 1902, number of pages: 7
  - #151: Wilhelm ?, birthdate: 1874, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 10
  - #152: Ferdinand Jansing, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 3
  - #153: Josef Nirschl, birthdate: 1897, World War I service: from 1916, number of pages: 4
  - #154: Paul Leimberg, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 8
  - #155: Otto Wolgast, birthdate: 1876, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 407691, number of pages: 7
  - #156: Paul Garisch, birthdate: before 1890, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 19
  - #157: Ernst Laube, birthdate: 1904, number of pages: 5
  - #158: Albert Kohler, birthdate: 1876, Nazi party number: 255766, number of pages: 2
  - #159: Heinrich Haar, birthdate: 1878, World War I service: unknown, number of pages: 2
  - #160: missing
  - #161: Schoepke, birthdate: 1886, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 31 (typed)
  - #162: Alfred Kotz, birthdate: 1886, World War I service: 1914-1918, Nazi party number: 244959, number of pages: 24
  - #163: Bemhard Lipki, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 14
  - #164: Hermann Nieswand, birthdate: 1889, World War I service: 1915-1918, number of pages: 7
  - #165: Josef Trzarka, birthdate: 1904, number of pages: 14 (not typed)
  - #166: Georg Schmidt, birthdate: 1887, World War I service: 1914-1918, number of pages: 16
  - #167: Wilhelm Domning, birthdate: circa 1895, World War I service: 1914-1916, number of pages: 14 (typed)
  - #168: Heinz Gefaeller, birthdate: 1909, number of pages: 11
  - #169: Bartsch, birthdate: 1877, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 105222, number of pages: 14
  - #170: Fritz Behrendt, birthdate: 1907, number of pages: 4
  - #171: G. Ullein, birthdate: 1907, Nazi party number: 10980, number of pages: 13
  - #172: Karl Schuck, birthdate: 1898, World War I service: from 1917, number of pages: 4
  - #173: Wilhelm Haas, birthdate: 1908, number of pages: 8
  - #174: Wilhelm Mayer, birthdate: 1903, Nazi party number: 23809, number of pages: 5
  - #175: Erna Siegfried, birthdate: 1883, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 855499, number of pages: 8 (not typed)
  - #175A: Karl Otto Zottmann, birthdate: after 1900, number of pages: 5 (typed)
  - #176: Helmut Flörkke, birthdate: after 1890, World War I service: yes, when unknown, Nazi party number: 8646, number of pages: 7
  - #177: Frau Nieke, birthdate: 1898, Nazi party number: 602554, number of pages: 16 (not typed)
  - #178: Keim, birthdate: 1901, number of pages: 7 (typed)
  - #179: D. Schäfer, birthdate: unknown, World War I service: unknown, Nazi party number: 39975, number of pages: 4
  - #180: Arthur Hessler, birthdate: 1903, Nazi party number: 48826, number of pages: 4